<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lean community blog (Posts about mathport)</title><link>https://leanprover-community.github.io/blog/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://leanprover-community.github.io/blog/categories/cat_mathport.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:"&gt;The Lean prover community&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 19:13:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Update on mathport (Dec 2021)</title><link>https://leanprover-community.github.io/blog/posts/intro-to-mathport/</link><dc:creator>Scott Morrison</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; is the tool we're planning on using to help us port &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt; to Lean 4.
It has mostly been written by Mario Carneiro and Daniel Selsam,
and Gabriel Ebner and I have been making some fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide some context, &lt;a href="https://github.com/leanprover-community/mathlib"&gt;mathlib&lt;/a&gt;
is the primary library for mathematics in Lean 3,
containing over 700k lines of code and growing fast!
Lean 4 now has a preliminary release, and we would really like to transition to
building a mathematics library in Lean 4.
While the type theory and kernel in Lean 4 are quite similar from a user point of view to Lean 3,
it is certainly not the case that we can run Lean 3 code in Lean 4.
Our aspiration is to achieve a "semi-automated" port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; tool first of all provides a complete binary level port of &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt;
(i.e. generating a Lean 4 &lt;code&gt;.olean&lt;/code&gt; file for every &lt;code&gt;.olean&lt;/code&gt; file in &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt;).
This means that you will be able to &lt;code&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; all files from &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt;,
as long as you don't expect to be able to look at the actual sources!
We have largely rejected the idea of a dual-compilation setup,
in which existing code stays in Lean 3, while new code is written in Lean 4.
The binary port could make this viable, but it seems complicated and fragile,
and the community is excited to take full advantage of Lean 4.
(A dual-compilation setup would not allow Lean 3 files to import from Lean 4 files,
so the version transition would have to be a cut across the import graph.)
Thus &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; further attempts a "best-effort" port of the source files,
translating Lean 3 syntax to Lean 4 syntax.
Right now, that "best effort" is not quite good enough!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is that this will steadily improve,
until we reach a point at which it become viable for humans
to finish the migration in an incremental fashion.
Notably, because of the size of &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt;, and its growth rate,
we have decided it is not desirable to "freeze" &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;
until very late in the process.
(Throughout this document, &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt; refers to the current mathlib repository,
but I'll try to consistently include the &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt; to disambiguate!)
Thus we will be regularly running &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on a continuously evolving &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; repository,
and for an initial period not depositing the output in the &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt; repository.
Nevertheless, &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; takes as input both &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;,
and attempts to automatically make use of the parts of the library which have already been ported,
by "aligning" definitions.
Thus once the output quality of &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; is sufficiently good,
we expect to be able to move files across to the &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt; repository
(starting from the bottom of the import hierarchy),
while continuing to re-run &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on the still evolving &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt; repository!
Eventually, however, we will declare "flag day",
at which point the &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; repository will stop accepting PRs for new material,
and we have a (hopefully brief!) intensive period of completing the migration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; makes no attempt to automatically translate the tactics that have been written in &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;.
Metaprogramming is sufficiently different in Lean 4 that this would be impossible,
and moreover there are significant stylistic differences when writing tactics in Lean 4,
so a literal translation would not be desirable.
This means that we have a huge amount of work remaining to re-implement all the &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; tactics in Lean 4.
We've already done a few important ones (notably &lt;code&gt;simp&lt;/code&gt; is implemented in Lean 4, and we have &lt;code&gt;ring&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;).
We would really like to preserve feature parity as we make the transition,
and so are hoping to re-implement tactics, rather than "dumb-down proofs" wherever possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The occasion for this blog post is that we now have continuous integration set up for &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;,
and a reasonably easy to use setup that lets you work with the output of &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;
without having to run it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll describe that setup up below, but first explain what sort of efforts are probably most useful right now to help the &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt; port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are approximately in priority order, in terms of my guess about what will hold up the port the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Porting missing tactics from &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;.
  This is still a huge task, and will not be automated in any way.
  If you've contributed tactics to &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;, please consider trying to port them to Lean 4.
  If you're interested in learning some Lean 4 metaprogramming, what better way to do that than porting tactics?
  We'll write more about this in a future post, with some pointers about places to get started,
  and how to hook up new tactic implementations to the existing tactic parsers that Mario has already ported to &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolve outstanding &lt;a href="https://github.com/leanprover-community/mathport/issues"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;.
  (On some issues there's already an indicated fix but it needs implementing/testing.
  Other issues still need diagnosis.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the &lt;code&gt;mathlib3port&lt;/code&gt; repository (instructions below), look at files (probably starting with "low-level" files),
  and identify things that &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; should be doing better. Check there isn't already an open issue, then open an issue.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note: at this stage I think it would be a bad idea to actually take a file from &lt;code&gt;mathlib3port&lt;/code&gt;, clean it up, and PR it to &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;.
  That will hopefully come later, but we need to fix many &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; issues first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead, it is fine to make changes &lt;em&gt;that you think &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; should be doing already&lt;/em&gt; and committing these on a branch,
  so that you can link to diffs when opening &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For now, don't worry too much about the state of proofs.
  We'd like to get to a state where the vast majority of &lt;em&gt;statements&lt;/em&gt; are correctly translated as soon as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are still many alignment problems between Lean 3 / &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; declarations, and Lean 4 / &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt; declarations.
  Sometimes these can be fixed by adding &lt;code&gt;#align&lt;/code&gt; commands in &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;. Sometimes they may turn out to be &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; bugs.
  Sometimes they will reflect deeper design problems we're going to need to talk about!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background: what is &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; consists of two loosely coupled components: &lt;code&gt;binport&lt;/code&gt; (largely Daniel's work), and &lt;code&gt;synport&lt;/code&gt; (largely Mario's work).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;binport&lt;/code&gt; constructs Lean 4 &lt;code&gt;.olean&lt;/code&gt; files, from Lean 3 &lt;code&gt;.olean&lt;/code&gt; files.
    It largely works, and means that you can import &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; content into Lean
    4 (as long as you don't expect to have source files!)
    This is what lets us do things like: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Mathbin&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#lookup3 algebraic_geometry.Scheme&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#check AlgebraicGeometry.Scheme&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yay, Lean 4 has schemes! :-)
To see this file in action, you should check out a copy of the &lt;code&gt;mathlib3port&lt;/code&gt; repository described below,
and make a new file there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;synport&lt;/code&gt; constructs Lean 4 &lt;code&gt;.lean&lt;/code&gt; files, on a "best effort" basis.
  (It uses both the output from binport, and Lean 3's &lt;code&gt;--ast&lt;/code&gt; output to guide it.)
  We should not expect that this will ever converge to a perfect translator.
  Instead the hope is that it gives us something that humans can plausibly improve to a complete translation of &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand how &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; (mostly talking about the synport part from here on) works,
it's important to understand that it is translating &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; to Lean 4 source code, "modulo" the current content of &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;.
That is, the premise is that as we progressively construct &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;
(whether by translating by hand, moving content from &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;'s output to &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;, or adding &lt;code&gt;#align&lt;/code&gt; statements)
the output from running &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; will change.
In particular, as &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; is translating each declaration,
it checks to see if a corresponding declaration in &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt; already exists, and is defeq.
If so, &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; will instead just use that declaration.
If not, &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; will make a copy, appending a &lt;code&gt;×&lt;/code&gt; to the name.
Sometimes these misalignments are due to an unintentional non-defeq, that can be fixed in &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;.
Other times, we genuinely want to change something in &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt;
(e.g. to use Lean 4's multiple parent structures, which are better than &lt;code&gt;old_structure_cmd&lt;/code&gt;).
As a result, we expect that some misalignments will persist throughout the &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;-assisted stage of the port,
and only afterwards will we polish these away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A detailed account of how binport and synport are working is beyond the scope of this blog post.
Hopefully we'll have one eventually,
but in the meantime &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fOO2fByx8tw"&gt;Mario's talk&lt;/a&gt; is very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What should I look at?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; takes considerable resources to run on &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;: approximately 3.5 hours, and 32gb of RAM.
So you'll probably want to look at artifacts generated by CI rather than running it yourself. There are four GitHub repositories you can look at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/leanprover-community/mathlib3port"&gt;mathlib3port&lt;/a&gt;
  should be most people's first stop. This contains a copy of the &lt;code&gt;.lean&lt;/code&gt;
  files produced by a recent run of &lt;code&gt;synport&lt;/code&gt;, in the &lt;code&gt;Mathbin&lt;/code&gt; directory.
  You should just be able to check out a copy of this repository, and open
  the folder in VS Code, to see the current state of &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; output.
  You can also try out the above example with &lt;code&gt;#check
  AlgebraicGeometry.Scheme&lt;/code&gt; in a fresh file here.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember the synported files are expected to be horribly broken;
  most tactics aren't implemented, and there are bugs around
  parenthesization of arguments, and name resolution!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good luck finding even a single file that compiles cleanly right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/leanprover-community/lean3port"&gt;lean3port&lt;/a&gt; is the corresponding repository
  containing a copy of a recent run of &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on the Lean 3 core library.
  It's less interesting perhaps, but also smaller and easier to inspect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/leanprover-community/mathport"&gt;mathport&lt;/a&gt; contains the code for &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; itself,
  as well as the continuous integration set up that runs &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on Lean 3 core and &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;
  every time there is either a PR to &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;, or a commit to master.
  The artifacts produced by CI appear at https://github.com/leanprover-community/mathport/releases,
  and the two repositories listed above have a &lt;code&gt;lakefile.lean&lt;/code&gt; that will download and unpack these artifacts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/leanprover-community/mathlib4"&gt;mathlib4&lt;/a&gt; is the current preliminary port of &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt; to Lean 4.
  Later, when &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; begins to stabilize,
  we will begin moving files from the output of &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; into this repository, but not yet.
  For now, this repository serves several purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primarily, it is the home for ports of tactics implemented in &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; to Lean 4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to build these tactics, a certain minimal library is necessary
  (e.g. for the &lt;code&gt;ring&lt;/code&gt; tactic, we need the notion of a &lt;code&gt;ring&lt;/code&gt;!)
  and we are constructing this by hand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is scope for experimental developments,
  but please don't just port parts of &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; to Lean 4
  for the sake of doing so.
  If you're investigating how some new Lean 4 feature might be used in the eventual port of &lt;code&gt;mathlib&lt;/code&gt;,
  it's okay to do so in this repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt; repository has fairly low standards:
we don't expect the full review process used in &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;.
Notable parts of the &lt;code&gt;mathlib4&lt;/code&gt; repository relevant for &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mathlib/Mathport/SpecialNames.lean&lt;/code&gt; contains a sequence of &lt;code&gt;#align&lt;/code&gt; statements,
  for cases where a definition in Lean 4 core has a different name
  from the name that would be produced automatically by changing case conventions from Lean 4 or &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mathlib/Mathport/Syntax.lean&lt;/code&gt; contains definitions of all the syntaxes of tactics currently implemented in &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;.
  These have been written by hand by Mario, and we should take care to keep these up to date.
  Please be careful editing this file,
  and we also need to remember to update it if any further changes to tactics land in &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;.
  Because in this file we only have the syntax statements,
  if you try to use the tactics here you will get &lt;code&gt;Tactic not implemented yet&lt;/code&gt; errors.
  If you would like to work on porting tactics, essentially this file is the TODO list!
  You should take the relevant syntax definitions,
  move them to their own file in the &lt;code&gt;Mathlib/Tactic/&lt;/code&gt; directory,
  and provide an implementation.
  Conversely, please do not start porting a &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt; tactic without faithfully reproducing the syntax,
  as this will then cause problems for &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;.
  It's completely fine to provide an interim port, that throws errors when encountering
  some of the bells and whistles specified by a syntax declaration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do I run &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt; in https://github.com/leanprover-community/mathport is currently the best available documentation for running &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;.
You will need to make sure you have &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cmake&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;elan&lt;/code&gt; installed on your system.
Basic usage is &lt;code&gt;make build source predata port&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These stages are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt;: compile &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; (which is written in Lean 4) itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt;: pull the relevant commits of Lean 3 and &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;, and do a little preparatory work in those directories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;predata&lt;/code&gt;: recompile the Lean 3 library and &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;, with &lt;code&gt;lean --ast --tlean&lt;/code&gt;, to generate the auxiliary files &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;port&lt;/code&gt;: run &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on Lean 3 and &lt;code&gt;mathlib3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running all of them in sequence is necessary if you're starting from scratch, but is painfully slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't really want to run &lt;code&gt;make predata&lt;/code&gt; yourself.
Typically you don't want to run &lt;code&gt;make port&lt;/code&gt; on the entire library either: you'd prefer to download an artifact containing the results,
but then re-run &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on a single file, in order to try out a bugfix to &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We provide artifacts for various stages of the build on the releases page of the &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; repository.
The script &lt;code&gt;./download-release.sh nightly-YYYY-MM-DD&lt;/code&gt; downloads one of these,
after which you can skip the &lt;code&gt;make predata&lt;/code&gt; and/or &lt;code&gt;make port&lt;/code&gt; steps
(you will still need to run &lt;code&gt;make build&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;make source&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've already got a local copy of the output of &lt;code&gt;make port&lt;/code&gt; (either by running it yourself, or using &lt;code&gt;./download-release.sh&lt;/code&gt;)
you can also use the &lt;code&gt;make TARGET=data.nat.bitwise port-mathbin-single&lt;/code&gt; target
(similarly for &lt;code&gt;port-lean-single&lt;/code&gt;) to run &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt; on a single file.
This is useful if you are testing a change to &lt;code&gt;mathport&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://leanprover-community.github.io/blog/posts/intro-to-mathport/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 11:41:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>